George Nelson & Co., Inc. Records
George Nelson & Co., Inc. Records
1948-1968
1957-1968
George Nelson & Co., Inc.
5.0 linear ft. (2 doc boxes and 17 tubes of rolled drawings)
Design descriptions and illustrations (1957-1968) and design tracings and drawings (1948-1968) of the American industrial and interior design firm.
149388
Biographical History
George Nelson (1908-1986) was an American writer, lecturer, teacher and designer. He is considered one of the founders of American Modernism, along with Charles and Ray Eames.
Although formally trained in architecture, over his career Nelson became known as a furniture designer, industrial designer, interior designer and exhibition designer. He was also an excellent writer and reporter; his series of interviews in the mid-1930s of important European designers (including Walter Gropius, Mies van der Rohe, Le Corbusier, and Gio Ponti) was published in Pencil Points and led to a position as an editorial staff writer at Architectural Forum. By 1945 he had become co-managing editor of the magazine. After World War II he began a forty-year association with the Herman Miller furniture company. His own company had a client list of Fortune 500 companies and Nelson continued to write, lecture, travel and design throughout.
[Portions of this biographical sketch adapted from "George Nelson," an essay appearing on the website of the American Institute for Graphic Arts.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George Nelson & Co., Inc. Records are divided into three series.
A small amount of Descriptive material about George Nelson and George Nelson & Co. is filed at the beginning of the collection.
Design descriptions and illustrations consist of photographs and printed descriptions of various industrial and interior designs by George Nelson & Co., Inc. These include offices, Herman Miller furniture, a United States Information Agency industrial design exhibit sent to the Soviet Union, and storage and module systems.
Design tracings consist of original drawings of Herman Miller furniture, offices, stores, a medical clinic, a ladder, showrooms, a traveling exhibit, a large number of clocks, a city hall, and other items.
Arrangement of the Collection
All material is arranged within each series alphabetically by folder title.
Related Material
has a substantial number of collections relating to industrial design. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Industrial Design; Nelson, George, 1908-1986.; George Nelson & Co., Inc.; Herman Miller, Inc.; Clocks and watches -- Design and construction.; Industrial design -- United States.; Industrial designers -- United States.; Interior decorators -- United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Drawings (visual works); Illustrations.; Photographs.; Industrial designers.; Interior decorators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Bulk, gift of George Nelson & Co., Inc., 1968.
Bruce Davidson photographs of sling sofa, gift of Ron Beckmann, 2011.
Inventory
- Descriptive material
  - George Nelson; George Nelson & Co., Inc., 1957-1968 (Box 1)
- Design descriptions and illustrations
  - Herman Miller
    - Action office, 1968; holograph reproduction and printed material (Box 1)
    - Brenner clinic, Lafayette, Indiana, 1968; printed material (Box 1)
    - Catenary Group and miscellaneous seating, 1968; holograph, reproductions, printed material (Box 1)
    - Chests, 1961-1962; printed material (Box 1)
    - Desk, 1960-1961; printed material (Box 1)
    - Executive office group, 1960-1968; holograph, reproduction, printed material (Box 1)
    - Fair chair, photograph (Box 1)
    - Sling sofa, 1968; holograph, reproduction, printed material (Box 1)
    - Sling sofa, photographs of sling sofa by Bruce Davidson; sign in one photo says "Catenary Group"; 10 items (Box 2)
    - Storage wall, 1961-1962; printed material (Box 1)
    - Travel exhibit, 1968; photographs, holograph, reproduction (Box 1)
    - United Airlines upholstery chair, reproduction of drawing (Box 1)
  - Howard Miller
    - Service module system, printed material holograph reproduction (Box 1)
  - United States Information Agency, Industrial Design USA exhibit; printed material (Box 1)
- Design tracings
  - Aluminum Extrusions, Inc. experimental ladder, 1965; 6 drawings (Tube 681)
  - B.H. Wragge Inc., 1954; display unites; rack details (Box 2)
  - Calvert Distilling, 1955-1956; decanters (Box 2)
  - Charles D. Briddell, Inc., 1954-1955; flatware, flatware cases, trays; includes 2 photographs and a clipping (Box 2)
  - CSS drawings, 12 drawings (Tube 688)
  - EOG revisions, 13 drawings (Tube 689)
  - Gartner and Bender, 1947-1948; exhibits, packings cases; includes two photographs; 6 drawings (Box 2)
  - General Lighting Co., 1947-1948; 1950; lamps; 6 drawings (Box 2)
  - Herman Miller
    - Action office chair, 1965; 9 drawings (Tube 673)
    - Action office, travel exhibit system, show rooms, 1959-1964; 70 drawings (Tube 674)
    - Armchair, 1950; described on sheet as "springy metal armchair" (Box 2)
    - Brenner Clinic, Lafayette, Indiana, 1966; 8 drawings (Tube 675)
    - Catenary Group and miscellaneous seating, 1948-1963; 78 drawings (Tube 676)
    - Club group, 1962-1963; 26 drawings (Tube 677)
    - Executive office group side chair, 1966; 17 drawings (Tube 678)
    - Executive office group, 1967; 5 drawings (Tube 679)
    - Fair chair, 1963-1964; 28 drawings (Tube 680)
    - Fair table, 1963-1964; 11 drawings (Tube 680)
    - Blow Spring, net seating, CSS foam core shelf, CSS grill cloth, 1961-1963; 26 drawings (Tube 680)
    - Radial action office, 1966; 19 drawings (Tube 681)
    - Show rooms, 1961-1964; 17 drawings (Tube 682)
    - Sling sofa and miscellaneous products, 1954-1965; 82 drawings (Tube 683)
    - Space divider, revised, 1965-1966; 36 drawings (Tube 684)
    - Service module system, 1964-1966; 55 drawings (Tube 685)
  - Holiday House, 1950; 8 drawings (Tube 674)
  - Howard Miller Clock Co.
    - Alarm clocks, 1955 (Box 2)
    - Ceramic clock, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Chess clock, 1959 (Box 2)
    - Chronopaks, 1948; 1952,; 1956,; undated (Box 2)
    - Clocknik, 1959 (Box 2)
    - Portable clocks, 1954; 1957 (Box 2)
    - Turbine clock, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Wall clocks, 1954-1957; 1959 (Box 2)
    - Clocks, miscellaneous, 1947-1960; includes clock parts, clock cases, grandfather clock, "sunburst" clock, more; also printed material and 4"x5" negatives of many clocks (Box 2)
    - Fireplace tools and andirons, 1950-1952 (Box 2)
  - Hunter Douglas, 1948-1949; exhibit; includes photographs (Box 2)
  - Miller's Bootery, 1958; 3 drawings (Tube 674)
  - Memphis, Tennessee City Hall, 1962; 36 drawings (Tube 686)
  - New York Times, 1954; Cross County Center (Box 2)
  - Pickard, Imc., 1949; cups, plates (Box 2)
  - Superior Electric, 1949-1950; lamps; includes photographs (Box 2)
  - United Airlines upholstery chair, 1962-1963; 27 drawings (Tube 679)
  - United States Information Agency, 1957-1961; exhibit (Box 2)
  - United States Information Agency, 1966; Industrial Design USA exhibit; 45 drawings (Tube 687)
  - Walker China Co., 1952-1953; serving items (cruet, gravy boat, pitcher, etc.); includes photographs (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 15 drawings (Tube 690)